<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The penitent sinners entertainement. Set foorth by Mr. Iohn Hill, Student in Diuinitie, and now Preacher of Gods Word at Dublin in Ireland</title>
            <author>Hill, John, preacher of Gods word at Dublin.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03351</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114518</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849743</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849743</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14910</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03351)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14910)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1352:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The penitent sinners entertainement. Set foorth by Mr. Iohn Hill, Student in Diuinitie, and now Preacher of Gods Word at Dublin in Ireland</title>
                  <author>Hill, John, preacher of Gods word at Dublin.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Beale, for Ionas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First leaf blank?.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14910:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14910:1"/>
            <p>THE PENITENT SINNERS EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERTAINE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT.</p>
            <p>Set foorth by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. IOHN HILL, Student in Diuinitie, and now Preacher of Gods Word at <hi>Dublin</hi> in IRELAND.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>AT LONDON <hi>Printed by</hi> IOHN BEALE, <hi>for</hi> IONAS MAN. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14910:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14910:2"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull and vertuous</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen M<hi rend="sup">is.</hi> TEMPERANCE CREW, wife to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Crew,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">is.</hi> 
               <hi>Mary Blinco,</hi> wife to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohn Blinco,</hi> I. H. deſireth all grace and peace vnfainedly to bee mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied: &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Odly, and chriſtian gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen, whom I loue in the truth,<note place="margin">2. Ioh. 1.</note> I hope I may ſpeake of you as did that worthy Apoſtle of the elect la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, who by the fruits of her piety and godlines, manifeſted her electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo you by the loue you beare tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards God, his ordinances, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, doe declare euidently,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.14</note> your
<pb facs="tcp:14910:3"/> tranſlation from death to life, and by your vertuous and holie liues, you demonſtrate freedome from ſin, which are of euerlaſting life. I haue made bolde (Christian Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) to patronize this ſmall worke vnder your fauours, in token of thankefulnes, for your many fauours I haue receiued from you; not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but ſmall things of this nature, will bee much respected, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly receiued; both in respect of your owne priuate gaine, as alſo the profit &amp; benefit, which the whole Church of God may reap &amp; gather fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it. Now if you, or the reſt of the body of Chriſt ſhall receiue any bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by it, for the furthering of that
<pb facs="tcp:14910:3"/> worke of repentanee, and ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life, giue God the glory and praiſe.</p>
            <p>And ſo J humbly take my leaue, commending you to the prouidence of God, and the word of his grace,<note place="margin">Act. 20.32.</note> which is able to build further, and to giue you an inheritance among all them which are ſanctified.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Steane</hi> 
                  <date>this <hi>20.</hi> of Aprill <hi>1612.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours in all chriſtian duties to commaund IOHN HILL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14910:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14910:4"/>
            <head>THE PENITENT SINNERS EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERTAINE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LVKE 15.20, 21, 22,</hi> &amp;c.</bibl>
                  <p>So he aroſe and came to his Father, and when he was yet a great way off, his Father ſaw him, and had compaſſion, and ran, and fell on his necke, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N all this parable of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and religious father, and a ſtubborne and impious ſonne, is prefigured and ſet downe, the vnſpeakeable loue and compaſſion of God our heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father to all his children in Ieſus Chriſt, which haue beene rebellious and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient before their calling.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14910:5"/>
            <p>In theſe words are ſet down two things, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt the duties of a penitent ſinner,</item>
                  <item>Secondly the promotion that the penitent perſon comes vnto.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In the dueties of the penitent perſon, there are two things to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>Firſt, a perſwaſion of mercy, &amp; ſure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of obteining compaſſion, if he did returne, implied in the word (Father) as if he ſhould haue ſaid; truth it is O Father, as my life &amp; works haue beene toward thee, I doe not deſerue to be thy ſon (as in the words following may appeare) but yet neuer the leſſe, I am perſwaded, that though I haue failed of my duty towards thee, yet thou wilt not faile of thy loue to me: &amp; although there be no deſert of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in me, yet I know there is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion for ſeeking for with thee: and this is the firſt ground the penitent perſon laies, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine mercie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the penitent perſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth his ſinne, whereby he had offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his father, for there muſt be a confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that as the childe is to be well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the loue of his father, ſo hee muſt be ill perſwaded of himſelfe, in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14910:5"/> of his ſinne, and therefore he ſaith, <hi>I haue ſinned againſt heauen and before thee:</hi> that is, againſt the God of heauen, and againſt thee my naturall father, and ſo I haue broken both the tables of the commandements.</p>
            <p>And he confeſſeth alſo, he was not worthie to be called a ſonne to ſo godly a father, or to receiue mercie that was ſo full of impietie, making himſelfe vile and baſe in his owne eyes, that he might be highly eſteemed in his Fathers eies: which is the firſt part.</p>
            <p>Now for the ſecond part of this text, which is the promotion the penitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhall be exalted vnto; ſet downe in the 22. &amp; 23. verſes, rendering a reaſon wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the father did thus promote him.</p>
            <p>The promotion ſet downe is this; the father ſeeing his riotous and vnthriftie ſonne returne home, with a broken and humble heart, and with a reſolution to become a new man, and rather deſiring his fathers loue then his goods, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently offers himſelfe to his childe, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could aske for his needs, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds his ſeruants to bring forth ſuch
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14910:6"/> things as his penitent ſonne wanted, and to giue it before he did craue it, for the father ſeeing his ſonne ſo well clothed with humilitie and with godly remorſe for his former life within, he wil not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect him, though he came poore and rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged outward, but cals for the beſt robe to couer him.</p>
            <p>The compariſon is taken from a King and a princelike childe, whoſe manner was to weare robes, and before the ſonne could aske for apparrell which he ſtoode in neede of, the father giues him a robe to put on: for ſeeing he had made himſelfe baſe in his owne eyes, he would cloath him royally that hee might ſeeme pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in his fathers eyes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And put a ring on his hand:</hi> that is, hee would not only giue him things for nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſity, but alſo to adorne &amp; beautifie him, &amp; as the Apoſtle ſaith, vpon our vncomely parts he will put more comelineſſe on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſhooes on his feete</hi>] And whereas he came barefooted to his father, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds ſhooes to be put on his feete, to keepe and preſerue them from thornes and ſtones that might annoy &amp; hurt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14910:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And bring the fatte calfe &amp;c</hi>] And whereas he came with a languiſhing ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke for want of meate (for before he had beene feeding amongſt ſwine) now he will refreſh him with a tender calfe; with pleaſant and comfortable meate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And let vs eat &amp; be merie.</hi>] Here is cauſe of mirth &amp; reioycing on both ſides; Firſt on the fathers ſide, that had loſt an vnto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ſonne, and now had found an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient ſonne, that went from him dead in his ſinnes, and returned quickned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the life of grace, that departed impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and returned humbled; in all which there was cauſe of mirth, and this cauſe the father renders himſelfe to his eldeſt ſonne; for my ſonne was dead and is now aliue, he was loſt, but is now found, &amp;c. Secondly there was cauſe of reioycing in the ſonne, becauſe he went from his father a dead man, and now he comes to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a liuing man: he went from him ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, proude, diſobedient, he returnes meeke, penitent, and obedient; in truth he departed from him a childe of <hi>Belia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and returnes to him the childe of God; in all which, there was great cauſe of ioy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14910:7"/> on both ſides. And ſo much for the ſomme and order of theſe words.</p>
            <p>The drift of the parable is, that if a godly father had a ſtubborne and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſonne that had departed from him; and ſpent his portion amongſt ryotous and lewd companions, yet if the father ſhould ſee his ſonne come home in that manner as is before alleadged, hee would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him againe, nay he ought (in truth) to entertaine him into his fauour againe with ioy, paſſing by all his ſtubborne and diſobedient behauiours, remitting all his faults, and receiue him as his childe againe, notwithſtanding all his offences.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>Then the application of this Parable is, that if the people of God haue beene A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates, reuolters, rebels, and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent vnto God, yet if they would from a plaine and an honeſt heart, returne to God by true and ſound repentance, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing their ſinnes with godly ſorrow, &amp; iudging themſelues not worthy of mercy; then wil the Lord, command his miniſters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> put on the rich robe of Chriſt his righteouſneſſe; and they ſhall be adorned with the graces and gifts of his ſpirit, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14910:7"/> ſhod with the goſpell of peace, and giue them the fleſh and blood of his ſonne, and the comfort and ioy of the ſpirit, and ſhal haue communion with God in Chriſt Ieſus, and this will God beſtow vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery penitent ſinner. For if a naturall pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent can ſhew ſo much mercie to ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracious and impious a childe when hee humbles himſelfe vnto him, that hath but a drop of mercie, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Ocean and Sea of mercie which is in God, how much more will God ſhew mercie vnto ſuch penitent and humble ſinners, that with ſence and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of their ſinnes and wants can come to God for mercie? And ſo much for the explication and application of the words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the ſonne ſaid vnto him father, &amp;c.</hi>] that is, the penitent childe ſaid vnto his naturall father. But before we come to gather any doctrine from the very words of the text; there ariſeth a doctrine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dependance of the words, in the 17 and 18 verſes; for when he came to himſelfe and was his owne man, and was awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of his ſpirituall frenzie, then he conſidered what he might doe; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14910:8"/> with this reſolution; <hi>I will goe to my father and ſay, &amp;c.</hi>] he begins to loath that courſe of life, and now doth put that in practiſe, which before he did but pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; and put that in deede, which before he had but thought in minde. From hence ariſeth naturally this doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> That where there is true repentance, there is not onely good purpoſes in the heart,<note place="margin">That reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in heart and action in life muſt goe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> but alſo good endeauors and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the life, not onely thinke and ſay well, but alſo practiſe and doe well. This we may ſee verie fitly proued vnto vs, in the examples of <hi>Ruth</hi> and <hi>Orpah,</hi> both of them purpoſed a like, for both proteſted to companie with <hi>Naomie</hi> to her owne countrie, to ſerue the God of heauen; but <hi>Orpah</hi> hearing the reaſons againſt that her purpoſe, returned backe to ſerue their idols:<note place="margin">Ruth. 1.</note> but <hi>Ruth</hi> hauing beene grounded by true repentance, to the loue of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion held on her reſolution, although her Mother in law did bring her ſiſters ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample as an argument to perſwade her to returne alſo, but ſhe replies againſt her Mothers ſpeeches, ſaying, <hi>intreate mee not to returne, for whether thou goeſt I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14910:8"/> will goe, and where thou dwelleſt I will dwell, thy people ſhall bee my people, and thy God my God.</hi> And what made <hi>Ruth</hi> ſo good of her word in this reſpect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe was come to her ſelfe, and true repentance, which made her thus purpoſe and performe.</p>
            <p>The like we ſee in <hi>Paul</hi> when he came to repentance, he reſolued to leaue his blaſphemie and perſecuting of the Saints of God, and ſo did: he was as good in acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as he was in purpoſe and affection. This doctrine being ſo; may alſo be far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirmed by reaſons drawne from the holy ſcriptures of God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe whoſoeuer comes to true repentance, will haue ſtronger rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> to doe well then to doe ill, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter arguments for godlineſſe, then he can for ſinne and wickedneſſe; as here we ſee this prodigall childe had; and ſo the Church in <hi>Hoſea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.7.</note> when the Lord met with them by his iudgements and ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the way, of inioying their outward bleſſings in that abundance which they had before time enioyed, and all becauſe they did attribute their plentie to their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14910:9"/> idols, but in their penurie and want they haue better reaſons; and ſay, I will goe and returne to my firſt husband (that is to Chriſt) for at that time I was better then now: as alſo in the fourteenth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when they come to repentance for their idolatrie,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.4.</note> they ſay; neither will we ſay any more to the worke of our hands, ye are our gods, for in thee the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe finde mercie; as if they ſhould haue ſaid, we will not be ſo ignorant and ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh any longer, to thinke that an Idoll or carued peece of wood can pittie vs or ſhew vs any compaſſion, for they are but our creatures, and therefore it argues that they ſhould rather kneele and bow to vs, then we to them; thus we ſee their iudgements are better informed when they came to repentance, then they were before, for repentance is a change of the minde, as it ſignifies.</p>
            <p>Secondly, looke what reaſons men haue to purpoſe well, the ſame reaſons they haue to hold out well; the ſame ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments which worke good affections in ones heart, will alſo hold out to bring foorth good actions in the life, as heere
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14910:9"/> the prodigall childe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, where true repentance is, there will be alſo godly ſorrow (for it cauſeth repentance,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.10.</note> as the Apoſtle ſaith) and where godly ſorrow begins, theſe effects will follow. Firſt, a holy care to leaue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and to practiſe that which is good. Secondly, a clearing of ones ſelfe from ones ſin. Thirdly, it will worke an indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and a holy anger againſt ones ſin. Fourthly, a godly feare to commit ſin the time euer after. Fifthly, a deſire to ſerue God more, &amp; to haue a greater meaſure of grace to pleaſe him better. Sixthly, a godly zeale of gods glorie, and after the ſpirituall meanes of ones ſaluation. And Laſtly, a holy reuenge vpon ones owne ſelfe, for the ſinnes whereby wee haue diſhonoured God: and theſe are the effects of true repentance. And to this effect doth the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeake, <hi>Cleanſe your handes ye ſinners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 9.8.</note> 
               <hi>and purge your hearts yee double minded</hi> But they might obiect; How ſhall we come to this purging and clenſing of both inſide and outſide? He anſwers them in theſe words following; ſuffer afflictions, and ſorrow
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14910:10"/> yee and weepe, let your laughter be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into mourning, &amp; your ioy into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe; as if he ſhould haue ſaid, if you wil purge your heart from ſin, and part the ſin from the ſoule, you muſt come to godly ſorrow for your ſins: for the nature of ſin is ſuch, that it is like a little childe, it will tarrie longeſt there where it is moſt made of, ſo if we will loue and make much of ſinne we ſhall haue his company, but if we will labour to afflict our ſoules for our ſinnes and ſorrow for it, we ſhall quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be rid of it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Sith it is ſo, that they that haue truely repented, will not onely haue good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes and motions, but alſo good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours and good actions, It ſerues, firſt for reproofe of ſuch perſons as would haue Gods children to thinke that they haue repented, becauſe they purpoſe to leaue their ſinnes: they will ſay, they haue a purpoſe to forſake their couetouſneſſe, to leaue their ſwearing, Sabboth breaking, their drunkenneſſe and ſuch like ſinnes, and will proceede no further: but aske them wherefore you would haue vs conceaue ſo well of you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14910:10"/> that you haue repented? becauſe we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe well; It is true, good motions are to bee reſpected, but if they doe not bring forth good actions, they are no better then quaulmes and paſſions that may be in verie wicked men and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites: for if there be good deſires in the heart, there will follow certainely good endeauours and actions in the whole man. <hi>Saul</hi> in a paſſion would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to <hi>Dauid,</hi> O my ſonne <hi>Dauid,</hi> thou art more righteous then I; and why did he preſently fall to perſecute <hi>Dauid</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? was it not becauſe the ſpirit of God neuer conuinced his conſcience of the ſinne, and he neuer came to godly ſorrow for the ſame, and therefore theſe were but paſſions, which died before they brought forth good actions? <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> alſo could come to this, <hi>I haue ſinned in betraying innocent blood:</hi> ſo farre he went well: but hee could not come to repentance to craue pardon, for had he repented hee might haue beene par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and if he could haue beleeued he ſhould haue beene ſaued, but doing neither, he was damned. Such paſſions and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14910:11"/> quaulmes had they, which in all the haſt, would goe and build vpon Chriſt: they did not conſider beforehand what char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges it would amount vnto, and whether they were able to vndertake ſo great a building,<note place="margin">Luk. 14.28.29.</note> and therefore hauing begunne, they could not proceede, but left off and were not able to finiſh it; So manie haue ſudden flaſhings and paſſions come into their mindes, to doe good things, but not conſidering the danger nor charges that one muſt be at, if they purpoſe to build vpon Chriſt, they let their ſute fall, and their purpoſes are quickly extinct and quenched before they come foorth to action. But theſe paſſions the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> compares to the morning dewe.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.9.</note> 
               <hi>O Ephraim what ſhall I doe vnto thee, O Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah how ſhall I intreate thee? for your good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is like the morning cloude, and as the Morning dewe it goeth away:</hi> that is, as ſoone as the ſunne ariſeth and ſhewes forth his beames of light, it lickes vp the dewe vpon the graſſe; ſo ſoone paſſeth your goodneſſe, and it is of no continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Of ſuch a nature are all theſe paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſudden quaulmes that many may
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14910:11"/> haue, and yet be verie ſinnefull and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: manie haue theſe flaſhings when they come to the Sacrament, and will haue theſe purpoſes to leaue their couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, their ſwearing, Sabboth breaking, and all their knowne and notorious ſinnes; and they will alſo purpoſe to pray more, frequent the exerciſes of religion more, and they will amend many diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which are amiſſe (if it might be all remedied with thoughts and purpoſes) but after the Sacrament they are as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and ſinnefull as euer they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and are neuer a whit the better in practiſe and conuerſation. Oh before they goe to the Sacrament they will pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to make ſatiſfaction to ſuch whom they haue wronged, and to liue as friends with them which in times paſt they haue much grieued; but let the Sacrament be paſt, there is no more hearing of ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, nor acknowledgement of iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and wrongs offered; yet we ſhall haue theſe vnconſtant men perſwade themſelues they haue repented, &amp; would haue others ſo to thinke and reckon of them: but ſuch muſt know that they haue
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14910:12"/> not yet repented, till theſe motions and purpoſes conceiued, bring forth good actions in life to be practiſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it ſerues for inſtruction, that ſeeing true repentance ſtands in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and doing, therefore if euer we will haue anie ſound comfort to our ſoules and conſciences, whenſoeuer the ſpirit of God hath put into our hearts good motions and good affections, let vs follow them hard to bring them to perfection, and then wee ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the worke (as the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh:) let vs labour to doe that which <hi>Barnabas</hi> exhorts the faithfull brethren at <hi>Antiochia;</hi> That with purpoſe of heart, they ſhould continue in the Lord. So let vs with all purpoſe of heart reſolue to leaue our ſinnes, and to practiſe holy and good dueties: let vs be like vnto this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall childe, which did purpoſe and practiſe, and ſo we ſhall haue a good teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie to our hearts that wee haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented.</p>
            <p>Oh but, I can no ſooner haue a good motion come into my heart, but Satan is readie to ſteale it out, and mine owne
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14910:12"/> corruption to extinguiſh it, before I can bring it forth to action? but labour to put in practize theſe rules which by Gods grace may helpe thee, to cheriſh good motions &amp; further them, that they come out to practiſe in thy life and conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if wee would haue our good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> to come to good deedes, wee muſt labour to come to ſound and thorough ſorrow of heart for ſinnes paſt; and let vs pluck the roots of ſinne vp by the wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hooke of godly ſorrow, and then wee ſhall bring forth good actions; and therefore the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> in the place before alleadged, exhorts his hearers to purge their hearts by godly ſorrow, for it will breake the cords of ſinne, and kill it by degrees. And to the intent that wee may ſorrow for ſinne, let vs bee frequent in meditating of what ſinne would haue done to vs, namely haue killed vs, (for the wages of ſinne is death) and expoſed vs to the euerlaſting wrath of God. Alſo conſider, that our ſins killed Ieſus Chriſt the Lord of life, they were the murtherers and betrayers of this iuſt one. And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14910:13"/> woe or miſerie hath or can befall vs in this preſent life, is the effect of theſe our ſinnes. Thus ſeriouſly pondering of theſe things, it will procure godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for ſinne, which godly ſorrow will produce good actions from good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, wee muſt bring good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and arguments againſt our corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Satans temptations, for if wee fall out with the diuell, and wee haue not better arguments to ſtand for good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, then hee hath againſt them, wee ſhall not bee able to hould out. For if <hi>Saul</hi> could haue had good arguments and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons when he purſued and fought againſt <hi>Dauid,</hi> if hee could haue conſidered, ſuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in fighting againſt <hi>Dauid,</hi> I fight againſt my beſt friend, and my faithfulleſt ſubiect, yea in ſo doing I ſhall fight againſt God, and mine owne ſaluation &amp;c. then hee would neuer haue followed him with ſuch a deadly malice. <hi>Iob</hi> that faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of God, hee had good reaſons to keepe him from ſinne, as appeareth, <hi>I haue made a couenant with mine eies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 31.1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>why ſhould I thinke on a maide, and what portion ſhould
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14910:13"/> I haue of God from aboue, and what inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance from the almighty from on high? is there not deſtruction to the wicked, and ſtrange puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the workers of iniquity?</hi> Why doth <hi>Iob</hi> bee ſo diligent in watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouer his ſenſes leſt hee ſhould offend? His reaſon is, if hee ſhould not haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to them, hee knew that the Lord would not regard him: and if hee ſhould haue let looſe his eies to behold wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, hee knew hee ſhould quickly looſe the fauour of God, and letting his eies take their liberty, hee ſhould ſuddenly haue taſted ſome miſerie: for hee knew there were ſtrange puniſhments for the workers of iniquity. Oh but who takes notice of ones thoughts and lookes? I may let my eies to take their liberty, and no man can perceiue it; nay, but <hi>Iob</hi> makes anſwere, <hi>Doth not God behold my waies and tell all my ſteppes?</hi> And although man cannot take notice of my luſtfull heart and eies, yet the allſeeing God doth behold it, and conſiders my ſteppes. Which made him not ſo much as wrong his pooreſt ſeruant hee kept: for ſaith he, <hi>If I did contemne the iudgment of my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14910:14"/> and of my maide, when they did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">13.19 ver.</note> 
               <hi>what then ſhall I doe when God ſtandeth vp? and when hee ſhall viſite me what ſhal I anſwer?</hi> And the reaſon why <hi>Iob</hi> durſt not bee froward with his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants; becauſe ſaith hee, <hi>Hee that made mee in the wombe, hath hee not made him?</hi> As if hee ſhould haue ſaid, it may bee my ſeruant may bee as dearely beloued of God as I my ſelfe, and hee may bee an heire of Heauen as well as I; at leaſt wiſe, I know wee are both his workemanſhip; and therefore I dare not vexe and iniure him. The whole chapter doth run vpon ſuch arguments and reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third thing to make one conſtant, is, when the Lord hath put into our mindes good motions, that wee delay not, but preſently and quickly put them in practiſe, and bring it forth into action, as the prodigall childe here did, for imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately as ſoone as this came into his minde, <hi>I will riſe and goe to my Father,</hi> hee delaied not, but roſe and came to his father. So the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> did, finding himſelfe out of the way,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.60.</note> hee ſaith, <hi>I made haſt and delaied not to keepe thy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:14910:14"/> Whiles the wound is greene, it is beſt to goe to the Surgeon: and wee haue an old prouerbe, It is good ſtriking, whiles the iron is hot; ſo when God puts into our hearts good affections, let vs quickly put them in practiſe; whiles hee warmes vs with the word &amp; Sacraments, let vs not delay but ſpeedily put it in acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and whiles hee ſpeakes by afflictions, let vs reſolue vppon a holy conuerſation. Now many when they come to the word, and hearing of ſuch duties which they ought to practiſe, as for prayer to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of euery one, at the leſt both mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening, the heart is preſently affected with it, and reſolue to practiſe it, but ſo ſoone as they are gone out of the Church, they defer the putting the duty in practiſe by and by, and ſo thoſe motions die before they come forth into action: and all becauſe they doe not ſpeedily goe about the worke; for as fier without ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie of fuell will quickly bee extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, euen ſo the delaying of putting theſe good reſolutions and deſires in practiſe, doe quickly goe out, and it leaues ſuch a deadnes and hardnes of heart, and makes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14910:15"/> one more duller to euery good dutie: wherefore whiles the heart is warme with any good motion, let vs ſpedily put it in practiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, to the end wee may haue all our purpoſes and deſires come to actions and true endeauours, wee muſt take heed of bad company, for they will quickly quench the good motions of the ſpirit, that they may neuer come forth to acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for if this prodigall childe ſhould vpon this determination haue gone and told his companions of this his reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they would haue quickly diſſwaded him from his purpoſe, but hee neuer goes to them to take their aduiſe, but of himſelfe reſolues and doeth. And this the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts the new conuerts vnto, ſaying,<note place="margin">Act. 2.40.</note> 
               <hi>Saue your ſelues from this froward generation,</hi> then they ſhould bee ſure to hold out, and not bee peruerted, nor our mindes altered &amp; changed. And ſo much for the firſt doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So hee aroſe, and came to his father, and ſaid to him, Father &amp;c.</hi> In this confeſſion which the prodigall childe doth make,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14910:15"/> hee begins with that which brought him home, euen the true conſideration that he had a Father, and the perſwaſion of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, if hee did returne, was it as brought him home, and ſo to repentance. From hence ariſeth plainely this doctrine.</p>
            <p>That the perſwaſion of mercie is a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> meanes to worke true repentance and ſound reformation in vs, no better a motiue to driue vs to true repentance, then the perſwaſion of mercie from God: for if this prodigal childe ſhould haue had this conceit to haue come into his braine, I will goe home, but my father will hit mee in the teeth of my ſinne and former behauiour towards him, or that it may bee hee will whippe mee out of his doores, or commit mee to the houſe of correction, and ſuch like, hee would neuer haue returned home, but rather haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his life amongſt the ſwine, then to haue gone to ſuch a cruell Father: but the perſwaſion of mercie driues him home. For proofe of this doctrine, the holy Ghoſt by the author to the Hebrues ſaith, <hi>For hee that cometh to God, muſt beleeue that God is, and that hee is a rewarder of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14910:16"/> them that ſeeke him:</hi> hee that will come to God and ſeeke him indeede, muſt bee perſwaded to finde him in mercy, and that he will beſtow his loue and fauour vpon him; for it is the perſwaſion of good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe that makes one goe to God: and therefore the Prophet ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 130.4</note> 
               <hi>That mercie is with thee that thou mighteſt bee feared.</hi> as if hee ſhould haue ſaid, I ſhould neuer haue reuerenced thy name, but that there is hope of mercie and grace from thee. Therefore the diuels hauing no hope of mercie, they doe not, nor cannot feare the Lord. Wherefore let vs ſet downe this as a maine concluſion, that if wee cannot haue mercie from heauen, wee ſhall haue mercie from no place.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth vrge the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> to the Romans, as a forcible argument to ſerue God. <hi>I beſeech you bretheren, by the mercies of God, that you giue vp your bodies a liuing ſacrifice, holy and acceptable to God which is your reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſeruice of God;</hi> where the mercies of God are a ſpeciall motiue to ſtirre them vp to ſerue God.</p>
            <p>Alſo the prophet <hi>Zacharie</hi> ſaith, <hi>I will
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14910:16"/> power vpon the howſe of Dauid and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of Ieruſalem the ſpirit of grace and prayers, and they ſhall looke vpon mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 12.12.</note> 
               <hi>whom they haue pierced, and they ſhall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for him, as one mourneth for his onely ſonne, whom &amp;c.</hi> This will make one turne to Chriſt, when they ſee their ſins ſo odious, as to bee the ſpeciall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to wound and kill the Lord of life, and alſo when they doe conſider that Chriſt gaue himſelfe for them, this infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite loue and mercie, will mooue them to true repentance and godly ſorrow.</p>
            <p>It is not miſery as can conuert one to God, and turne one from ones ſinne; for then the diuels might haue bin conuerted before this time, for they are in anguiſh and perpetuall miſery: and <hi>Iudas</hi> might haue repented, for hee was ſenſible of horrour enough in his conſcience, but that rather did driue him from God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could not apprehend the mercie and kindneſſe of God.</p>
            <p>The reaſons to proue this doctrine are.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe till ſuch time one haue this perſwaſion one ſhall neuer come to <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> true confeſſion, which is one part of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14910:17"/> ſound repentance, and one will neuer confeſſe ones ſinnes without hope of mercie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, becauſe it is vnpoſſible that one ſhould pray aright, without one haue this perſwaſion of mercie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt ſets downe this, as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all true prayer, <hi>Our father which art in Heauen.</hi> For wee can neuer haue any comfort that our ſinnes are pardoned till wee can boldly goe to him in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of mercie. And though wee haue failed of our duties towards him, yet hee will not faile of mercie to vs, becauſe hee is our Father.</p>
            <p>Sith this is ſo, that the perſwaſion of mercie is a ſpeciall meanes to ſtirre vs vp to true and ſound repentance, it ſerues for a double reproofe of two ſorts of people.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Firſt of thoſe impious beaſts and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the world, that if one reproue them for their blaſphemy, ſwearing, Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both-breaking, drunkenneſſe, filthines, and ſuch like ſinnes; they preſently haue an anſwere for to cloake it, and extenuate it; oh but the Lord is mercifull: but to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14910:17"/> whom? to ſuch as continue in this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety? no: but doeſt thou abuſe the mercie and long ſuffering of God, that ſhould leade thee to repentance, and ſo thereby doeſt harden thy heart in impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency, and doeſt heape vp as a treaſure vnto thy ſelfe, wrath againſt the day of wrath, that thus on earth adde drunke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes to theft: theſe abuſe the name of God, and it is more fearefull to abuſe the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, then the lawe. It were a ſinne to breake the poſitiue lawe of a Prince, but more if hee ſtampe vnder his feete the priuy ſeale of the Prince, wherein his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don is written, thus diſgracing &amp; mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, and yet hope for mercie of him. Wee would count it the part of a mad-man. Such are the dealings of all ſuch preſumptuous wretches, they breake the poſitiue lawes of the King of Heauen and earth, and continue in the breach of the firſt and ſecond table of the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements; and not only ſo, but abuſe the priuie ſignet of God, and hope for mercie notwithſtanding their vngodlines: but ſuch muſt know, that the Lord will not bee mercifull to ſuch, but contrariwiſe,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14910:18"/> the wrath and ſeuerity of God. For if a Father ſhould vſe all the duties of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to his child, and yet hee would bee very rebellious to his Father ſtill, and all becauſe his Father is louing and kinde vnto him; ſuch a childe would be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cenſured to bee a very vngracious and wicked child: how much more are ſuch impious and in a high degree vngodly, which dayly diſpleaſe God, blaſpheme his name, prophane his Sabbaths, &amp;c. and all becauſe God is mercifull, and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous? But theſe make a contrary vſe of the loue of God, then the Prophet <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> exhorts the faithfull vnto, in the place before alleadged, that they ſhould looke vpon him whom they had pierced, and lament, but the wicked wretches looke vpon him, and gnaſh their teeth at him, and blaſpheme his name, and ſo are made impenitent.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, it ſerues for reproofe of ſuch whom God hath afflicted with many croſſes, and they ſee in themſelues many ſinnes, and much corruption; and then vpon this they ſit themſelues downe, whyning and crying, and neuer ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14910:18"/> one foote to goe to God for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and pardon of their ſinnes, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing of the Croſſe. Thus they thinke there is leſſe mercie in God, then is in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for if a godly parent, though his childe haue played the vnthrift, and rebellious childe, yet if hee would come home with ſorrow and humilitie, and acknowledge his faults, he will preſently receiue him and ſhew him mercie, and yet we cannot perſwade our ſelues of the like ſucceſſe with God. Thus wee make Gods of our ſelues, and make the mercifull God more cruell then man, which is moſt fearefull once to thinke. Can wee forgiue the faults and wrongs committed one to an other, that haue but a drop of mercie, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon of that Ocean &amp; Sea of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and pitty in God, and ſhall wee not bee fully aſſured wee ſhall haue pardon and forgiuenes of ſinnes, if wee come to him by repentance? Let vs not diſhonour God ſo highly, to make God leſſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull then mortall man: for man hath made no promiſe to remit the wrongs and iniuries offered to him; but God hath bound himſelfe by couenant, yea by
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14910:19"/> oath to pardon the ſinnes and offences committed againſt him. Againe, man cannot forgiue all wrongs perfectly, but hee would haue ſome ſtirrings and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in his minde againſt the party: but if wee had all the ſinnes of <hi>Cain, Saul, and Iudas,</hi> yet if wee could come to God with faith in his mercie, and godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and repentance for our ſinnes, hee would receiue vs to mercie, and giue vs a generall pardon of all our ſinnes, and ſeale it with the blood of the euerlaſting couenant. Wherefore let vs no longer looke vpon the greatnes of our ſinnes, but vpon the mercie of God, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds our ſinnes, nor on the greatneſſe of our croſſes, but vpon the infiniteneſſe of gods compaſſion, and kindneſſe, and let vs reſort to him in hope of mercie,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond vſe ſerues for inſtruction vnto euery one, that whatſoeuer our croſſes bee, or how many ſoeuer our ſins bee, or how great ſoeuer our offences be, yet let vs haue a reſolution to goe to God, and wee ſhall finde mercie: for wee are in this caſe fit ſubiects for his mercy to worke vpon: for mercy pleaſeth him,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14910:19"/> &amp; he is greatly pleaſed to ſhew mercy to ſuch. Let vs conclude before hand, that if we reſolue to bee true vpright chriſtians, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may boldly call God Father; &amp; if wee can perſwade our ſelues wee are his children, wee may beleeue wee ſhall finde mercie at his hands. Wherefore let vs confeſſe our ſins, and leaue our ſins, and wee ſhall finde mercie. For if a Iudge of an Aſſize ſhould ſay to a felon or ſome malefactor in the Gaole, If you will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe your theft or treſpaſſe, and reſolue to become an honeſt man, I will pardon your fault, and not onely ſo, but you ſhall bee made a Iuſtice of peace, or ſome great man; hee would vpon this promiſe bee moued quickly to confeſſe his felony, and forgoe his theft; now the Iudge of all the world offers vs this large promiſe of mercie, that if a ſinner will truely, and from his heart confeſſe his ſinnes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue to leaue them, hee ſhall haue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and not onely ſo, but hee ſhall bee made a King, and prieſt vnto God the Father, and this preferment wee ſhall come vnto, if wee come vnto God in a right manner.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:14910:20"/>
            <p>Oh but how might I doe to come to bee perſwaded of mercy, if I come to God?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt pray vnto God that hee would giue vs his holy ſpirit, which feales vnto our hearts this perſwaſion of mercy, as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe wee are ſonnes, God hath ſent forth the ſpirit of his Sonne into our hearts, which cryeth, Abba Father.</hi> The ſpirit of Chriſt doth worke this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, that God is our Father, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this aſſurance, wee ſhall bee forced to cry <hi>Abba Father,</hi> and going to our beſt Father, wee may bee ſure to finde mercie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, wee muſt offer vp our ſoules and bodies, &amp; deſire in all things to ſerue him, &amp; to keepe all his commandements, then we ſhall receiue mercy from God, as that holy man <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>O Lord I beſeech thee, let thine eare hearken to the praiers of thy ſeruant, and to the prayers of thy ſeruants, that deſire to feare thy name.</hi> So that if wee can but truely deſire to repent, and deſire to keepe all Gods commaundements, and deſire to bewaile all our ſinnes, and to ſtriue againſt all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14910:20"/> and it is certaine wee ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine mercy at the hand of God. For if a chriſtian parent commaund his childe to doe a thing, and if hee doe it willingly and cherefully, and though hee doe it not ſo perfectly as the parent himſelfe, yet hee will take it in good parte, becauſe his child endeuoured to performe it, as well as hee could: how much more will God our heauenly Father accept of the poore deſires and endeauours of his children, when hee ſees in them a willing deſire to doe well? But if our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires bee good and true, then there is a vſing of all good meanes, and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to accompliſh the thing deſired, or elſe it is but a ſlouthfull deſire, and it may not bee called truely a deſire; elſe, but a luſt: but if wee deſire to repent, and to beleeue, and alſo vſe all good meanes to repent and beleeue, and be humbled becauſe we cannot repent and beleeue, as wee ſhould, the Lord will haue mercy vpon ſuch holy deſires, and accept the will for the deede. And ſo much for the ſecond doctrine.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:14910:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And when he was yet a great way off, his father ſaw him, and had compaſſion, and ran &amp;c.</hi> In all theſe words is ſet downe the affection and loue of the father, vpon the reſolution of his ſonne; the ſonne was but comming, but the father is run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: hee comes ſlowly for mercie, but the father is ready and forward to ſhew mercy: which ſhews the wonderfull rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe of God to ſhew mercy to a peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinner, that comes to God for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. From hence wee learne this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> That God is very ready to ſhew mercy vnto euery penitent ſinner, that comes to him with a broken and humble heart.</p>
            <p>That a penitent ſinner can noe ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner looke for mercy from God, but hee is ready to ſhew mercy to them.</p>
            <p>That God is more ready to ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, then penitent ſinners can bee to ſeeke for mercy. This wee ſee in a naturall father, to his penitent childe here; now a naturall parent, hath made no ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to ſhew mercy to his childe, but our heauenly Father hath made a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to euery penitent ſinner to ſhew him
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14910:21"/> mercy; againe, a naturall parent cannot ſhew mercy, and kindneſſe to his childe, without great coſts and labour, but our heauenly Father, hee can ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy without any trouble or charges, for it is his name to bee mercifull.</p>
            <p>Now if this bee in a naturall parent, that he will ſhew mercy, though hee haue not promiſed, yea though it bee to his great coſt, and paines; how much more will our heauenly Father ſhew mercy to his children, ſith hee hath promiſed, and is both able and willing, with eaſe to doe it. If this bee in man, which hath but a droppe of mercy, in compariſon of God, what may a penitent ſoule expect at the hands of God, who is infinite in mercy, and pitty, to his? This doctrine may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fitly bee proued, by the example of Gods dealing with <hi>Dauid:</hi> that when he had committed two greeuous ſinnes of adultery, and murder, and had almoſt ſlept a twelue moneth in them, in ſo much that the Lord is faine to ſend a Herald of armes to him, to awaken him out of his ſpirituall ſleepe, and to helpe him out of his ſinnes, and to bring him to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14910:22"/> but the Prophet could no ſooner remember his ſinnes to him, but hee doth imediatly confeſſe his ſinne, and hee no ſooner acknowledge and confeſſe his ſinnes,<note place="margin">2. Sa. 12.13.</note> but the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> by the mouth of the Lord doth pronounce his pardon: yea before hee did aske it, the Prophet tels him, <hi>the Lord hath put away thy ſinne, &amp; thou ſhalt not die.</hi> This alſo we may ſee proued, in that Pſalme which is intituled <hi>Dauids learning,</hi> wherin the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet confeſſeth, <hi>when I held my tongue, my bones conſumed, and when I roared all the day.</hi> That is, as long as I did diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſeemed to cloake, and hide my faults, I was plagued and tormented, ſo that roared like an vnreaſonable beaſt through paine: <hi>then I acknowledged my ſinne vnto thee, neither hid I mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, for I thought, I will confeſſe againſt my ſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 32.45</note> 
               <hi>my wickedneſſe vnto the Lord, and thou forgaue the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my ſinne.</hi> Thus wee ſee, hee could no ſooner confeſſe, but hee had pardon, both from the guilt, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his ſinne, and hee could no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſeeke for mercy, but hee obtained
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14910:22"/> mercy at Gods hands.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> ſhewes the mcreie of God vnto true repentant ſinners where hee ſaith,<note place="margin">Iſay 64.5.</note> 
               <hi>Thou diddeſt meete him that reioyced in thee, and did iuſtly, they remembred thee in thy waies: behold thou art angry, for wee haue ſinned, yet in them is continuance, and wee ſhall be ſaued:</hi> where the Prophet ſpeakes of the Lord, after the manner of men, that he is ready to meete them halfe way (as it were) that ſet themſelues in truth, and vprightneſſe, to confeſſe their ſinnes, and meete him by repentance, hee will meete them ſwiftly, though they come but ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and though they come heauily, yet they ſhall depart ioyfully. And the ſame Prophet ſaith in the next chapter of the Lord, <hi>before they call, I will anſwere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay. 65.24</note> 
               <hi>and whiles they ſpeake, I will heare.</hi> This wee may ſee in the prodigall childe, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee asked for foode, cloathes, and other things, which hee ſtood in neede of, his father beſtowes it vpon him, and before hee could make an end of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his ſinnes, hee falles vpon his neck, and embraceth, and receiueth him
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14910:23"/> to fauour. Now there are reaſons to proue that this doctrine is ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Becauſe it is both the name and nature of God, to bee mercifull and ſhew pitty, as the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> affirmeth, <hi>hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth not his wrath for euer, becauſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy pleaſeth him.</hi> When a man is come truely to confeſſe his ſinnes with ſorrow, then God muſt needes ſhew mercy to him, for mercy pleaſeth him; A ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty will perſwade a man to doe that which hee delighteth in, and takes pleaſure in the doing of it: euen ſo God is eaſily drawn to ſhew mercy to the penitent ſinner, becauſe hee delights in it, and is well pleaſed to ſhew mercy. Oh but how ſhall I know that I ſhall receiue mercy from him? why ſhould wee call it in queſtion, if wee bee penitent, for it ſtands vpon his trueth and couenant, to pardon the ſinnes of the elect, and for the certainety thereof hee hath bound himſelfe by an oath to fulfill it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, becauſe ouer and beſides our owne prayers, (to obtaine his fauour and mercy) we haue the prayers of Chriſt our mediatour to helpe vs: and although
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14910:23"/> the elder brother of this prodigall childe, did grudge and thinke much that his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould ſhew ſubh kindnes to his yonger brother, which had bin ſuch an vnthrift; yet wee haue our elder brother Ieſus Chriſt, to make continuall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto his Father for vs, &amp; in our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. Now if a naturall father can ſhew ſuch mercie to his childe, when the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der brother ſpeakes againſt him; how much more ſhall our heauenly Father ſhew mercy to vs, when as our elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is willing and ſpeakes for vs, and hee is as ready to pray for mercy for vs, as our Father can bee to giue mercy to vs.</p>
            <p>Sith it is ſo, that God is more ready to offer mercy to penitent ſinners, then they can bee to aske for mercy; The vſes ſerue;</p>
            <p>Firſt for confutation of the Papiſts, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> that in their diſtreſſes and troubles, will not goe to this mercifull God, but vnto Saints and Angels for helpe; alack they take a wrong courſe to forſake this piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God, whoſe name is to ſhew mercy, and whoſe nature is to delight in mercy,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14910:24"/> and runne to a Saint; this is palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble blindneſſe, to forſake the creatour, and receiue the creature: it is as if one ſhould forſake to fetch water from the Sea, where is enough, and runne to a channell that is dry; but if God will not ſhew mercy, who will? and if hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, who can? ſhall wee finde more mercy from a Saint or Angell, then from the mercifull God, of whom the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe findes mercie? This argues they know not Gods name, for then as the Prophet ſaith; <hi>They that know thy name, will truſt in thee, for thou neuer faileſt them that ſeeke thee</hi> They are not perſwaded of this name of God, for then they would not ſeeke to Saints or Angels, but vnto God, who neuer failes any that ſeeke to him in truth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, this ſerues to ſhew a great deale of corruption in our ſinfull hearts, and nature; for although wee goe not in our diſtreſſes and miſeries, to Saints or Angels, yet wee ſeeke vnto ſuch as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will not, or elſe cannot helpe vs, and ſo forſake him, where wee might alwaies ſpeede and neuer faile, if wee ſeeke him
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14910:24"/> with an honeſt heart, &amp; indeede; for he would meete vs halfeway, if hee did but perceiue in vs but a true purpoſe to come to him. One godly teare of true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, with a faithtfull prayer vnto God, is able to doe vs more good, and to helpe vs out of our diſtreſſes, then all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward meanes of friends, money, goods, and ſuch like things, in all this world can doe. But here is our diſtruſt in God, that wee haue more hope that wee ſhall ſpeed better of our neighbours, and friends in time of trouble, then of God: but this comes to paſſe, becauſe wee doe not aſſure our hearts that hee loues vs in Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.26.</note> according vnto Chriſts prayer, that hee made for all the elect: for if wee did, wee would more depend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon God, and leſſe rely vpon men, more ſeeke to him for helpe, and leſſe truſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on outward things.</p>
            <p>Thirdly it ſerues for inſtruction, that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> wee ſhould euery one ſeeke vnto God, chiefely, in all our diſtreſſes and troubles, for to bee deliuered. If one will goe to one that is able, let vs goe to God, and if wee would ſeeke to one that is willing,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14910:25"/> let vs ſeeke vnto God, for there is neither will, nor power wanting in him, if wee come to him in truth. And if wee would haue mercy from God, let vs draw neere to him with penitent and broken hearts, waſhing our ſoules with godly ſorrow for ſinnes, and then the blood of Chriſt ſhall be as water to purge vs from all our ſinnes and iniquities whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Oh but my ſinnes are ſo many, I dare not goe to him! but let not that hinder thee from goeing to him, for the more wee ſee our ſinnes, and the greater bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den wee feele them, the more bold wee may bee encouraged to goe to him for mercy: for onely ſuch are the gueſts which Chriſt inuites, and cals, and vnto whom in truth hee was ſent: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee ſaith; <hi>Come vnto mee all that are heauy-laden, and I will eaſe you. Mathew</hi> 11.28.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, ſith God is ready to ſhew mercy to euery penitent ſinner, when hee comes to him, and neuer caſts his faults in his teeth. Let this ſerue for imitation, vnto euery one of Gods children, that would bee ſaid to bee like God, let them
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14910:25"/> bee eaſily intreated to bee reconciled, when matters of differences fall out, and let vs ſo pardon, and forget the wrongs and iniuries offered vs, that wee neuer vpbraide the parties in the teeth for the ſame. Oh let vs neuer burſt out with theſe ſpeeches, I wil forgiue him, but I wil neuer forget him, or I will neuer loue him againe, &amp; ſuch like ſpeeches, but this is to be far vnlike God: oh but the offence that is offered mee, is ſuch a great wrong, as no man could put it vp; but bee it that it is ſo grear, haue not you offered God greater wrongs? and yet hee hath pardoned you, and will not you forgiue him this one wrong that is done to you? in truth this argues that you haue not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of the loue of God in Chriſt, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forgiue your brother ſo ſmall a fault. But if you will be like God, (which all his children muſt reſemble in truth, if they meane to come to heauen,) you muſt labour to remit great wrongs, and ſmall wrongs, and all and euery one, and neuer vpbraide them in their teeth of it, but bury it in obliuion, and neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it: and ſo wee ſhall bee like to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14910:26"/> our heauenly Father. And let vs bee ſo farre from reuenging wrongs offered vs, that wee pray for them that hate vs, and bleſſe them that curſe vs, ouercoming euill with goodneſſe, as wee are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded. And ſo much for this firſt doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the ſonne ſaid vnto him, Father, I haue ſinned againſt Heauen.</hi> Here is the confeſſion of this prodigall childe, to his worthy father: as if hee ſhould haue ſaid, truth it is, I haue ſinned againſt the God of Heauen, in ſinning againſt you my naturall parent, and whereas before I thought my ſelfe to good to bee your childe, or to remaine within your houſe, yet now I change my opinion, and thinke not my ſelfe worthy to bee ſonne to ſo good a father, and that the worſt place in your familie is to good for mee, ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward a ſonne. And ſo much is to bee vnderſtood in the 21 verſe. But in that hee confeſſed hee ſinned againſt God, by diſobeying of his father, wee learne this doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> That thoſe which wrong men, doe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14910:26"/> ſinne againſt God: In iniuring men on earth, wee ſinne againſt the Lord in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. This is proued by the wiſe man, where hee ſaith; <hi>Hee that mocketh the poore reprocheth him that made him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17.15.</note> 
               <hi>hee that derides the creature, doth mocke the creatour: and he that contemnes the worke, doth by conſequence ſpeake againſt the workeman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo the Apoſtle proues the ſame when he ſaith;<note place="margin">Cor. 1.8.12</note> 
               <hi>Now when yee ſin againſt the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren, &amp; wound their weeke conſciences? ye ſinne againſt Chriſt,</hi> Where the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſheweth, that thoſe offences that are committed againſt the weake brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, doe redound to bee committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt: when they offend the members, they ſinne againſt the head.</p>
            <p>And therefore Chriſt ſaith;<note place="margin">Math. 18.6</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall offend one of thoſe littleones that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in mee, it were better for him that a milſtone were hanged about his necke, and that hee were drowned in the depth of the Sea.</hi> Thus wee ſee that if any offend the leaſt chriſtian, he doth offend Chriſt, and ſhall bee ſeuerely puniſhed: and this Chriſt will doe, when hee will paſſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14910:27"/> of condemnation againſt the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, <hi>I was a hungred, and yee gaue mee no meate, I was thirſty, and yee gaue mee no drinke, I was a ſtranger, and yee tooke me not in to you,</hi> and ſo forth. Where for the omitting of good duties, to bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the members of Chriſt, Chriſt takes the omiſſion of dutie, as done to himſelfe, and ſo a ſin done againſt God.</p>
            <p>The reaſons to proue this doctrine are.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, becauſe whenſoeuer wee wrong men, we breake the commaundement of God, and ſo wee muſt needes ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God. Now hee commaundes a law of equity; that, that I would that men ſhould vnto mee, doe I the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and hee bids vs doe good vnto all, &amp;c. Now when wee breake any of the diuine lawes of God, wee treſpaſſe againſt God, and this made <hi>Dauid</hi> to cry out;<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſinned againſt thee, againſt thee onely.</hi> But one might haue ſaid, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> you haue wronged <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his wife away? It is true, but I haue broken Gods law, and ſo ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, by killing <hi>Vriah.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:14910:27"/>
            <p>Secondly in wronging men, wee ſinne <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> againſt God, becauſe euery man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man carries the image of God, and ſo wronging the perſon of man, hee wrongs the image of God. And this <hi>Iob</hi> did conſider well of, which did ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him from wronging his ſeruants, as appeares by his words, <hi>what then ſhall I doe when God ſtandeth vp, and when hee ſhall viſit mee, what ſhall I anſwere? hee that hath made mee in the wombe, hath hee not made him? hath not hee alone faſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioned vs in the wombe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sith that God is offended, when man <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> is wronged, it ſerues, firſt for inſtruction, that wee ſhould take heede how wee doe wrong any man, or woman; and not to ſay, I care not for him, or her, for hee is but a baſe perſon, a man of no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, &amp;c. Nay but take heede how you iniure and wrong him, bee hee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo baſe in your eies: hee may bee an heire of Heauen, and a true child of God, and at leaſt hee carries the image of God, in ſome meaſure vppon him: and ſo you cannot ſafely wrong him, but you ſinne againſt the God of Heauen: and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14910:28"/> beſides you are forbidden to wrong any, bee they neuer ſo baſe and vile. But ſuch perſons as wrong theſe baſe ones, (as they terme them) dare not wrong a greater perſon: becauſe, if they ſhould, they might haue the law inflicted vppon them, and ſo thereby bee brought into danger, as to bee caſt into priſon, &amp;c. But to hurt and trouble a poore chriſtian, that they feare not to doe; but ſuch muſt know, there is as great danger, to wrong the pooreſt chriſtian, as in iniuring the greateſt perſonage in the world: for the wrong done to the member, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounds to the head, and the hurt offered to the poreſt chriſtian, is a ſinne againſt Chriſt him ſelfe: and as the Prophet <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charie</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Zach. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that toucheth you, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the apple of his eye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is none would endure one to ſtirre or row a thorne, or any ſuch like thing, in ones eie but one ſhould feele it; for there is no place ſo tender about one as the apple of the eye; how much more ſenſible is God of the iniuries, and wrongs offered vnto his children, and cannot endure them, that thus touch
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14910:28"/> him, in ſo tender a place, as to wrong his beloued ones, ſuch ſhall bee ſure to ſmart for it. And if the Lord would not haue <hi>Balaam</hi> to wrong his Aſſe, much leſſe will hee ſuffer wicked men to wrong his children: but many care not what iniury they doe to others, ſo they can act it cunningly, and worke it ſubtilely, that they may not bee ſeene, or ſo that the lawes of the Realme will not take hold of them. As the wife many times, towards the husband, ſhee cares not what hard ſpeeches ſhee giues him, becauſe there is no humane lawes againſt her for it: but ſuch wiues muſt know, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God is offended when their husbands are thus wronged by them, they ſhall not goe vnpuniſhed, vnles they repent; for Gods law and precept is violated, that commaunds wines to bee obedient to their husbands in the Lord. So many times the husband, hee wrongs his wife in word, countenance, and ſomtime in their diſordered paſſions in blowes, when in truth there is no cauſe offered him; but this argues there is but a little feare of God in him, that thus will wrong his
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14910:29"/> owne fleſh: ſuch men little conſider when they reuile their wiues, they reuile God himſelfe, and when they thus wrong them they ſinne againſt him, for they breake his commaundement, that chargeth euery husband to loue their wiues, as Chriſt loued his church, and to to dwel with them as men of knowledge, &amp;c. But vnles ſuch husbands come to true repentance for the iniurie thus offered to their wiues, God will ſurely plague and puniſh them, as a ſinne done againſt his maieſty.</p>
            <p>So many maſters which deale cruelly towards their ſeruants, becauſe they bee poore and meane, both in parentage and outward friends, they care not what wrong they doe vnto them, and how bad they vſe them; but ſuch maſters muſt know that in wronging their poore ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, they ſinne againſt God, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer their ſeruants bee baſe in their eies, yet they may be members of Chriſt, and heires of heauen, or at leaſt, hee that made you in the womb, made him in the wombe alſo, and in wronging them, you wrong the image of God in them; but
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14910:29"/> if they bee Gods ſeruants, as well as thine, and if they bee the children of the Almighty, then they touch the Apple of his eie: and better it were a milſtone were hanged about your necke, and that you were caſt into the depth of the Sea, then that you ſhould offend one of theſe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ones. And if Chriſt will pronounce ſentence of condemnation againſt ſuch (at his ſecond comming) which omit workes of mercie to his members, how much ſorer puniſhment ſhall ſuch haue, which wrong and hurt the members of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſith God is offended, when <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> man is iniured, it ſerues to teach vs, if wee haue wronged any, either in word, or deede, whether it bee husband to his wife, or the wife towards the husband, the childe to the parent, ſeruant towards the maſter, or the ſuperiour to the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; wee muſt not onely content our ſelues with confeſſing our fault, to the party thus wronged, but wee muſt alſo acknowledge it to God, whoſe laws wee haue violated and broken, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, when hee had committed adultery with
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14910:30"/> 
               <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> and killed <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> againſt thee, thee only haue I ſinned, and this <hi>Dauid</hi> would haue done, put caſe that <hi>Vriah</hi> ſhould haue liued, hee would haue firſt gone to God, and haue confeſſed his fault, before hee would haue gone to <hi>Vriah,</hi> (though both are required.) Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in many are very faulty, for they thinke, if they haue fallen out with their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and bee made friends againe, they haue done enough, and they ſuppoſe then they may lawfully come to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe they bee at peace with men, and haue gotten reconciliation with thoſe which they haue offended: it is true, if you had only offended man, then it were ſufficient if you had done no more, but ſith there is two perſons of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, the perſon of God, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of man; therefore there muſt bee reconciliation got of both, and the fault muſt bee acknowledged to God, as wel as to man, before we can come prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly to the Sacrament. At for example, If a man rob another by the way ſide, and from him take his purſe, and by this fact, hee breakes not only the lawes of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14910:30"/> King, but alſo the lawes of God; it were not ſufficient for the offender to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the fault to the party robbed, and pray him forgiue him, but hee muſt alſo get his pardon from the King, whoſe law hee hath broken, or elſe it may bee hee may die for his treſpaſſe, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the party robbed hath forgiuen him.</p>
            <p>In like manner, when wee haue wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged man, wee muſt not only ſeeke to him for to haue the wrong remitted, but alſo to God, whoſe law wee haue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that hee would forgiue it, and ſo wee muſt ſeeke for a pardon from God, as well as from men, or elſe we are lyable to haue his iudgments executed vpon vs.</p>
            <p>The want of this duty, is the cauſe why thoſe agreements that are ſo made vp, betwixt man and man, are ſo ſoone bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that within two or three daies (if occaſion bee offered) their hatred is as great againe as euer it was, and that is becauſe they bee at ſo little paines, and ſo ſmall charges, to ſue out theſe pardons, whereas if they bought them at a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14910:31"/> rate, and went to Heauen for them, by ſound repentance, confeſſion, and godly ſorrow, they would not bee ſo haſty to fall out with their neighbours againe.</p>
            <p>And the neglect of this duty is the cauſe, that many times wee haue ſuch checkes, and galles in our conſciences, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee make vp theſe wrongs offered, ſo ſleightly, wee goe to men whom wee haue wronged, but neuer to God, whom wee haue offended. Wherefore to auoide all inconueniences, which may follow vpon this wrong doing, let vs bee exhorted for the time to come, not only to goe to men, but a ſo to ſeek to God, for an acquittance: for hauing a pardon from the King, wee neede not feare the arreſt of a petty conſtable, or any inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our officer belonging to him. And ſo much for the handling of this point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And againſt thee:</hi>] that is, againſt thee my naturall parent, I confes I haue ſinned. From hence wee learne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>5</label> That it is not enough to confeſſe our ſinnes vnto God, but wee muſt alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe them to men, ſo far as wee haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14910:31"/> them. That knowen wrongs done againſt men, muſt bee acknowledged and confeſſed to men.</p>
            <p>This duty Chriſt doth exhort vnto,<note place="margin">Math. 5.23 24.</note> 
               <hi>If thou bringeſt thy gift vnto the Altar, and there remembreſt that thy brother hath ought againſt thee, leaue there thy offering, before the Altar, and goe thy way, firſt bee reconciled to thy brother, and then come, &amp; offer thy gift.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus wee ſee, if any hath ought againſt vs, that wee haue done them any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wrong wee muſt firſt, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally, goe and ſeeke reconciliation, for it is fit, if wee haue ſet a howſe on fire, we ſhould ſeeke to quench it, and put caſe wee haue neglected it vntill wee come to the Sacrament, yet wee ſhould then leaue our offering, and defer it, and returne to the party offended, and acknowledge the wrong, crauing pardon for it, for God is willing, and content that his owne ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice ſhould wait and ſtay, till that duty bee performed, and then come, and offer thy gift.</p>
            <p>Alſo in an other place,<note place="margin">Luk 17.3.4</note> our ſauiour ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts them to this duty, ſaying; <hi>If thy
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14910:32"/> brother treſpas againſt thee, rebuke him and if hee repent, forgiue him, and though hee ſinne ſeauen times in a day, and ſeauen times in a day returne againe vnto thee, ſaying, it repenteth mee; thou ſhalt forgiue him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There Chriſt would haue vs to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to forgiue wrongs, if the parties of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending will returne, and confeſſe their faults, for if they performe their duty, to ſeek reconciliation, we muſt not fail of our mercy to giue them remiſſion ſo far as lies in our power.</p>
            <p>Reaſons to proue this doctrine to bee true, are theſe. Firſt, it is drawne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> equity, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> that he that vnlawfully hath made a wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſhould vſe all lawfull meanes to heale the wound, and he that through paſſion ſets the houſe on fire, ſhould alſo with diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion labour to quench the fire. And hee that through folly hath wronged his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, muſt alſo by wiſedome ſeeke to right him againe. And this the law that is imprinted in nature will teach, that what wee would that men ſhould doe vnto vs, that wee ſhould doe vnto them. If this were practiſed, wee ſhould not ſo much fall out into diſtempers, paſſions,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14910:32"/> froward ſpeeches, and vniuſt actions, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one another.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if when wee haue wronged <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> men, we would acknowledge the wrong, to the party offended, it would bee the beſt way to pacifie their hearts, and to make them thinke well of vs, and to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect vs, notwithſtanding the wrong done vnto them; and if wee would greiue our ſelues, becauſe we haue greeued them, and offended them, it would bee a ſpeciall meanes to make the party wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, to ſend vp many a hearty praier vnto God, for the offendour, that hee would vouchſafe to forgiue him, as well as him ſelfe. And this benefit will confeſſion of wrongs doe to the party; it will make our foe, to become our faithfull and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing friend.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if wee did vſe to confeſſe the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> wrong, as ſoone as wee haue done a wrong, it would make vs beware and take heede of committing of wrongs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. For if the wife hauing wronged her husband, would ſeriouſly conſider; what? I haue wronged my husband, and if I purpoſe to haue forgiuenes, I muſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14910:33"/> not only confeſſe the iniury to God, but alſo to my husband. This would make the wife aſhamed, and ſo by that meanes breake the necke of ſinne, and it worke humility in ones ſoule, ſo that one ſhould haue little luſt to fall out, and to wrong one againe.</p>
            <p>Now fith it is not enough to confeſſe and acknowledge the wrongs done to men, vnto God, but wee muſt confeſſe it to the parties offended.</p>
            <p>It ſerues firſt for reproofe of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that come to this point, that if they haue wronged any one, they will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it to God, and ſo thinke they haue done enough, but they muſt as well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it to man, as well as to God; for the plaiſter ought to goe as far as the ſore. Oh but what neede there bee any confeſſion to men, when wee haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed it to God, for none can forgiue ſinnes but God, but you muſt not only repent to God in Heauen, but alſo aske forgiueneſſe of men on earth, or elſe the Lord will not forgiue it: for hipocrites may doe the one, as <hi>Iudas, Saul,</hi> &amp;c. But thoſe which are truly vpright, will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14910:33"/> them both; but ſuch as neglect this duty to man, as well as performe it to God, argues they are in loue with their ſinne, and loth to haue their nature hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and their ſinnes pardoned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it ſerues for inſtruction, that therefore wee ſhould take heede, that we doe not wrong any one, for this will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low confeſſion and acknowledgment of the fault, not only to God, but the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty offended, for vntill wee confeſſe the wrong to the party, and get reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him, wee muſt not looke God in the face, nor cannot haue entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to any of Gods ordinances, as the word, Sacrament, prayer; for the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a loue feaſt for the ſheepe of Chriſt, and not for wrauling doggs.</p>
            <p>Now if the husband haue giuen any angry and churliſh ſpeeches to his wife, whereby ſhee hath taken them to heart, and troubled her minde, let him confeſſe the fault to her before hee approch nere vnto God in any of his ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>So if the wife haue wronged the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, the childe the parent, the ſeruant
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14910:34"/> the maſter, or any one, one another, let them humble themſelues who ſoeuer is guilty, and acknowledge the fault to the party offended, and ſo get reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or elſe wee cannot lift vp pure hands, without wrath, as the Apoſtle ſpeakes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note>Oh but, hee whom I haue wronged is not in the country, how ſhould I get re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with him? ſhall I not come to the Sacrament, and other ſeruices, till I haue confeſſed my fault to him, that I know not where hee is?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note>Yes thou maiſt come to the word, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, prayer, and the reſt, if thou canſt finde in thy ſelfe a willing heart to aske forgiuenes, if hee were in the Country, as alſo if thou doeſt reſolue within thine owne ſoule, that if euer the party offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded returnes againe into the Countrey, thou wilt performe this duty. Yf this bee in thee, thou mayeſt frequent Gods ordinances.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note>But what if the party offended will bee ſo ſtubborne, that he refuſe to be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and will not pardon mee, though I acknowledge the fault, and offer ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the hurt &amp; wrong committed?</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:14910:34"/>
            <p>But doe thou the worke of the Lord,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> and let it not bee thy default, and then thou ſhalt finde mercy of God, for hee will not deale with vs according to the ſucceſſe with the party, but according to the vprightnes of our heart, and in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming our duties, let vs doe the worke, and then the Lord will reward vs. And ſo much for this point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am not worthy to bee called thy ſonne, &amp;c.</hi> Here is the laſt duty of this repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ſinner: his humility, hee is well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of his father, but ill perſwaded of himſelfe. This doctrine wee learne from hence.</p>
            <p>That true repentance makes one ſee his own vnworthines: the better repentance, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>6</label> the more humility: they will eſteeme of God to bee great, but themſelues to bee baſe, as wee ſee this prodigall childe: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, there was no place in the family good enough, and now there is no place in the houſe that is bad enough, hee is not worthy in his owne eies to bee ſonne to ſuch a godly father. This wee may ſee prooued out of the examples of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14910:35"/> all holy men, when they came to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as <hi>Iacob; I am leſſe then the leſt of thy mercies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nehemiah, Ezra, Daniel,</hi> they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, and confounded in their faces, and that ſhame and confuſion of face be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iob 39.37.</note>And this wee may ſee in holy <hi>Iob,</hi> when the Lord had ſhewed him his power and wiſedome, hee anſweres the Lord, <hi>Behold I am vile, what ſhall I anſwere thee, I will lay my hand vpon my mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in an other place, <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeakes when hee came to repentance for all his paſſionate and diſtempered words in his afflictions;<note place="margin">Iob 42.6.</note> 
               <hi>I abhor my ſelfe, and repent in duſt and aſhes.</hi> And beholding Gods purity, hee ſaw more euidently his owne impurity, and cauſe enough to humble and abhorre himſelfe for his filthines, and no longer to ſtand out with God in his owne innocency.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Paul</hi> that worthy Apoſtle, and ſeruant of God, when hee came to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, hee confeſſed, that hee was not worthy to bee called an Apoſtle, becauſe he perſecuted the Church of God.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:14910:35"/>
            <p>In all which examples, we ſee theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men when they came to repentance, they were baſe and vile in their owne eies, and ſaw their owne vnworthines.</p>
            <p>The reaſon to proue this doctrine is.</p>
            <p>Becauſe repentance opens our eies to ſee more perfectly Gods glorious purity, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> and ones owne vilenes and impiety, which will ſo reflect vpon vs, that it will make one low and baſe in ones own eies, as may bee ſeene in the Prophet,<note place="margin">Iſai 6.5.</note> when hee cryed out, <hi>Woe is mee I am vndone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am a man of polluted lippes, and I dwell in the midſt of people of polluted lippes.</hi> Where God appeares vnto the Prophet, and his maieſty being ſo perfect, that it reflects vpon him, whereby hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues the more his owne vileneſſe and pollution, yea euen in his beſt parte, as his lippes, which had deliuered the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of God very faithfully. So in truth when wee come to ſee the multitude of our ſinnes, and the hainouſenes thereof, wee ſhall bee made quickly low enough, and bee forced to cry out with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall childe, <hi>I am not worthy to bee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thy ſonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:14910:36"/>
            <p>Sith it is ſo, that true repentance makes vs ſee our owne vnworthines;</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> It ſerues firſt for reproofe of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which ſtand vpon theire owne wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines and goodnes, they will ſay, they hope they are in as good a caſe as the beſt of them all, that mourne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and keepe ſuch a doe about repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, &amp; they ſtand vpon it, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to be reckoned both with God and man, as well as the beſt of them that go to ſermons, and they liue as wel as the beſt of them all, and ſuch ſpeeches they are full of. But theſe ſpeeches argue that they haue not repented, but are as yet vnder the power of ſinne, and in the ready way to damnation: for all theſe are but phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaicall conceipts, for hee cryed out hee was not like other men, extortioners, vniuſt, adulterers, or euen as this publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, &amp;c. but I doe this, and this: and thus boaſting himſelfe of his owne goodnes, he ſhewed himſelfe a moſt cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed perſon; but the poore publican ſtood not vpon his owne worthines, but runnes vnto God for mercy, and hee is ſo aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that he could not look vp his eies to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14910:36"/> Heauen, but ſmote his breaſt, ſaying; <hi>O Lord bee mercifull vnto mee a ſinner.</hi> I tell you this man departed to his houſe iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied rather then the other. Thus wee ſee the eſtate of theſe boaſters that ſtand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theire owne goodneſſe and worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whereas a poore ſinner that feeles his ſinne, doth wonder at the goodneſſe of God, that ſhould ſaue ſuch a vile wretch as himſelfe, ſo far is hee from boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in himſelfe, that he glorieth in God alone.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it ſerues for conſolation <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> vnto ſuch which in truth can finde their ſins out, and thereby can perceiue their owne vnworthines; they conſider what they were before their calling, and what they are ſince: they ſee what originall ſin hath brought vpon them; blindnes, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, deadnes, hardnes of heart, &amp; in briefe a little diuell incarnate, which makes the pore ſinners to cry out, that they are not worthy of the leaſt of Gods mercies, they cry out, ſhame and confuſion belongs to them, and with the Church, it is the Lords mercy, wee are not confounded &amp;c. Theſe may comfort themſelues, for
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14910:37"/> it is a good argument that they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, and that they haue put on a great part of their wedding garment: for this is a great part of a chriſtians worthines, to ſee his owne vnworthines, and it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, if wee can bee baſe in our owne eies, wee ſhall bee precious in Gods eies, and thoſe which ſee how vile ſinne hath made them, ſhall bee made excellent in the righteouſnes of Chriſt. Theſe gueſts are the welcome gueſts vnto the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords ſupper, for theſe are inuited; <hi>Come vnto mee, all that are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy laden, and I will eaſe you.</hi> And ſo much in breife for the handling of this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then the father ſaid vnto his ſeruants, bring forth the beſt &amp;c.</hi> Now the father is ſo glad of the returne of his wandering childe, that hee preſently receiues him to fauour, and hauing his fauours, hee hath all his wants ſupplied. From hence wee learne this doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>7</label> That when wee haue the fauour of God, wee ſhall haue euery thing wee ſtand in neede of. Nothing ſhall be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14910:37"/> when wee haue Gods fauour.</p>
            <p>Loue is bountifull, and liberall, cheif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in God. This <hi>Dauid</hi> knew to bee the fountaine of all good, when hee heard them cry out, <hi>Who will ſhew vs any good?</hi> but hee cries,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4, 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>Lord lift vp the light of thy countenance vpon vs. Thou haſt giuen me more ioy of heart, then they haue had, when their wheate and wine did abound.</hi> Hee had more good by Gods fauour and countenance, then the worldlings could haue in their greateſt plenty of outward things.</p>
            <p>This made the Church in captiuity bee ſo earneſt in this petition, that ſhe repeats it thrice, noting thereby the excellency of it; <hi>Reſtore vs againe O God of hoasts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 80</note> 
               <hi>and cauſe thy face to ſhine vpon vs and wee ſhall bee ſaued.</hi> So that if God would looke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them with a gracious counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, they ſhould quickly haue a riddance of their miſeries.</p>
            <p>And this the Lord himſelfe preſcribes as a notable meanes to bring proſperity to ſoule, body, ſtate, &amp;c.<note place="margin">2. Chron 7.14.</note> 
               <hi>If my people vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom my name is called vpon, doe hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelues, pray, and ſeeke my face and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14910:38"/> turne from their wicked waies, then will I heare in Heauen, and bee mercifull to their ſinne, and will heale their land.</hi> When they performe theſe duties, (as among the reſt) to get and obtaine my fauour, then will I ſhew theſe mercies, I will heare as a mercifull and heauenly Father to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them from their troubles, and bring them ſuch comforts as they ſtand in neede of.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Sith it is ſo, that Gods fauour will make ſupply of all ſuch things as wee neede, it ſerues to teach vs, if wee would bee furniſhed throughly with all good things for our ſoules and bodies, for this life and a better, then let vs labour to get peace with God, and to ſeeke his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour before all things, for it giues true intereſt to all things, and it will bring all needefull things. If a man haue the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour but of an earthly Prince, what outward thing can hee want? If pore, hee can make him rich, if baſe, yet hee will make him honorable, if in debt, hee will diſcharge it. If this bee in a mortall man, to him that hee doth fauour, what may wee expect from the fauour of the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14910:38"/> King of Kings? In his fauour there muſt needs bee life, and proſperity. If the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor but of an heatheniſh King could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote <hi>Mordecai</hi> to ſuch an outward ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and dignity, from ſo baſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected eſtate, that hee muſt haue a royall robe and apparrell to bee cloathed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, a gallant ſteede and horſe to bee mounted vpon, and a crowne of gold vpon his head, and no baſe perſonage to bring all theſe preſents to <hi>Mordecai,</hi> but by the hand of one of the Kings moſt noble Princes; what ſhall wee haue, wee may conclude, that God doth fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, when <hi>Mordecai</hi> ſhall haue ſo much, when an earthly King doth meane to honour. It is certaine the King of Heauen will bee far more liberall and bountifull to his fauourites, then an earthly Prince can poſſible bee, for hee will put vpon them the royall robe of Chriſts righteouſnes, which is the beſt roabe, &amp; they ſhal all be Conquerours o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all their ſpirituall enemies, and bee made Kings and prieſts.</p>
            <p>And they ſhall haue all theſe ſpirituall graces and gifts, deliuered to them by
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14910:39"/> the King of Heauens Ambaſſadours, the faithfull miniſters of Chriſt, by the word, and Sacraments. And this ſhall hee haue, whom the King of Heauen will fauour indeede. And ſo much for this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then the father ſaid vnto his ſeruants.</hi> In that the father when hee would giue any gift to his ſon, doth it by the hand of his ſeruants, wee learne this doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>8</label> That when God doth purpoſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow vpon any of his children, any ſauing grace, or ſpeciall gift, hee doth it not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly from his owne hands, but by the hands of his ſeruants the Miniſters. The Miniſters of God, are the conduit pipe to conuay graces and gifts to the children of God.</p>
            <p>I cannot haue time to proſecute this point, becauſe the time is paſt already, and therefore I will leaue it, and only touch a little of an other doctrine, and ſo wee will make an end for this time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the father ſaid, bring forth the beſt robe, and put it vpon him, and put a ring on
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14910:39"/> his finger, and ſhooes &amp;c.</hi> In that, comming to his father, with repentance and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, the father giues him all things hee ſtood in neede of, comming ragged, hee hath the beſt robe put vppon him, and a ring vpon his hand for ornament, and ſhooes &amp;c. From hence wee learne this doctrine.</p>
            <p>That whoſoeuer comes to God with an humble heart, and true repentance, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>9</label> ſhall receiue at Gods hands whatſoeuer hee ſtands in neede of. That repentance will get any thing at Gods hand, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for neceſſity, but alſo ſomething for delight.</p>
            <p>This may bee proued by the words which Chriſt ſpeakes to the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> ſhe boaſted of her plenty, when as ſhee was full of penury: ſheee thought ſhee had all things: when ſhee wanted all good things, yet Chriſt promiſeth her if ſhee would come to him, hee would fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh her with all good things, and if ſhee would receiue his councell, he would decke her with the richeſt iewels, and therefore hee ſaith,<note place="margin">Reu. 3.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>I councell thee to buy of mee gold tryed by the fier, that thou maiſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14910:40"/> bee made rich, and white raiment that thou maiſt bee cloathed, and that thy filthy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes may not apeare, &amp; anoint thine eies with eie ſalue that thou maiſt ſee, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in buying and ſelling, there muſt bee ſomwhat giuen and receiued. Now therefore ſhee muſt ſell her ſinnes, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and godly ſorrow, and ſhe muſt eſteeme of the fauour of God, and graces of Chriſt in lieu thereof: and this being done ſhee ſhall receiue in ſteed of her pouerty, the riches, and graces of Chriſt, and his ſpirit; and in ſtead of her filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhe ſhall haue the white rayment, and righteouſnes of Chriſt, to couer her, and all her wickednes, and infirmities ſhall bee taken from her: and whereas ſhee was blinde, that ſhall bee remoued, and her eies ſhall bee opened, and her vnderſtanding enlightened, by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of wiſedome &amp; knowledge.</p>
            <p>But what neede I goe from my text to proue this, that when wee come to true repentance, wee ſhall haue all good things beſtowed vpon vs? For here the father commaunds the ſeruants to fetch out the beſt robe: now all the robes that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14910:40"/> are in Gods wardrobe, are all beſt robes. For the thiefe vpon the croſſe that died with Chriſt, and repented and beleeued in him, had one of the beſt robes, as well as <hi>Abraham, Iacob,</hi> or any of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes; and they are all long robes, not ſcanting, but couering and hiding all our filthines with the Kingly robes, and ſhining garment of Chriſt. And hee will not content himſelfe to giue him a robe, but hee will alſo put a ring vpon his hand, for ornament; ſo the Lord will decke and adorne euery true repentant ſinner, with the comely graces and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of his ſpirit.</p>
            <p>And whereas hee comes bare-footed, and ſurbated with trauell, he puts ſhooes vpon his feet. So the Lord, when one comes to him by true repentance, he will beſtow vpon him the ſhooes of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the Goſpell of peace, that he may bee able to walke through all rough and hard waies, yea the ſhadow of death, and ſhall not bee hurt.</p>
            <p>And whereas hee came home with a languiſhing ſoule, for want of foode, the father calls for the fat calfe, and the beſt
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14910:41"/> cheere hee had, he beſtowes vpon him.</p>
            <p>So the Lord beſtowes vpon the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinner, the beſt diet, and banquet. Many times, earthly fathers haue it not ready, wherewith they may entertaine their children, but God hath it alwaies in a readines, a feaſt of fat things, euen a feaſt of fined wines, and fat things full of marrow, of wines fined, and purified, euen the body and bloud of Chriſt, for God the Father makes the feaſt, Ieſus Chriſt is the matter of the feaſt, and the Holy ghoſt the applier of it. Now in the Sacrament the worthy receiuers, receiue all theſe things, &amp; all needfull things ſhal bee ſupplied vnto them thereby: for if the eating of one fruit which was forbidden vs, brought ſuch an vniuerſall miſery vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the poſterity of <hi>Adam,</hi> how much more may we bee perſwaded that the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the bread, and the drinking of the wine in the Sacrament, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, will bring a more happy eſtate to the worthy receiuers, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other loſt, for this meat will not only nouriſh vs, but cure vs alſo. The elder brother (which is to be vnderſtood of the Iewes) hee was
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14910:41"/> angry, and repined at the kind dealing of his father towards his yonger brother: but now our elder brother Chriſt Ieſus, is well pleaſed with euery penitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, which comes to his Father, and makes interceſſion for them. And if an earthly parent will thus loue a yonger ſonne, which hath bin a lewd and rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous companion; how much more will our heauenly Father entertaine euery pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent perſon, that comes to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the body and blood of Chriſt, with reſolution to cleaue vnto God, they ſhall bee ſure to haue ſupply of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer grace they ſtand in neede of.</p>
            <p>So alſo the father reioyceth, and they are merry that his wandring ſonne is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home againe; and therefore the father makes a feaſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt God the Father maketh a feaſt for euery penitent ſinner, and hee reioyceth to ſee a ſinner to returne to him,<note place="margin">Ier. 32 41.</note> for <hi>hee delights to doe ſuch good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo Chriſt himſelfe reioyceth to ſee ſuch as conuert vnto him, for it is meate and drinke for him to doe his Fathers will.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:14910:42"/>
            <p>And the Angels in Heauen doe both deſire and reioyce at the conuerſion of a ſinner, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.7.</p>
            <p>And not onely ſo, but all the Saints &amp; Church of God, that heare of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of a ſinner, and addition to the Church, will magnifie God, and reioyce vpon it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there will bee a feaſt of ioy to the party conuerted, when hee ſees a wretched creature to come to the feaſt of God, that before was eating with ſwine, hee now comes to feaſt with God, the whole Trinity: before to feede vpon ſwiniſh meate, and now to eate no worſe then the body and blood of Chriſt, by faith in the Sacrament, and to afford vs theſe benefits. Firſt thereby to bee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from our ſinnes, through the blood of Ieſus Chriſt. And ſecondly, to receiue ſtrength and increaſe of graces, as faith, repentance, loue, and other ſauing gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces more. And not only ſpirituall gifts, but alſo temporall for body, ſtate, name, and euery thing that is needefull for vs, in euery point according to the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which the Lord hath made in <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:14910:42"/> 36.25. &amp;c. And if wee can come to the Sacrament with true feeling and ſeeing the want of grace, and alſo being pained with carrying ſuch a loade of ſinne, wee may bee aſſured to bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdened of the one, and our want ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in the other, and ſo wee ſhall bee made fit gueſts for the Lords ſupper. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label>
            </p>
            <p>Sith it is ſo, that whoſo euer doth come to God with true repentance, and reſolution to cleaue faſt vnto him, ſhall haue as much as hee ſtands in neede of, it ſerues for encouragement to poore pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſinners, that haue committed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great ſinnes, that they ſhould come to God, and make their mone vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that hee would vouchſafe to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done all their ſinnes, and giue them ſuch graces, whereby they may be aſſured of his fauour; for certainely if wee come with repentance, and reſolue to become new men, and to ſticke cloſe vnto him, wee may expect to receiue at his hands euery thing which wee ſtand in neede of.</p>
            <p>Others muſt bee intreated before they wil doe any thing, but God will giue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee aske, yea hee will meete a peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14910:43"/> ſinner halfe way, if they will but looke towards him, hee will runne tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards them with mercy. Oh but I neuer looke to liue in credit againe, and to haue a merry day, my miſeries are ſo many? indeede if you purpoſe to keepe your ſinnes, you muſt bee ſure to keepe your ſorrowes; but if you will come to true repentance, and ſeeke vnto God, he can and will ſupplie all your wants, and whatſoeuer croſſes and loſſes you haue ſuſtained, hee is able to make vp your broken eſtate, heale your name, and ſet you in as great proſperity againe as euer you inioied; for he makes poore, &amp; makes rich, and proſperity comes from him, and he giues to all, and hits none in the teeth. God hath in his wardrobe all kindes of apparrell ready made, if wee ſeeke vnto him.</p>
            <p>And there is no ſoule ſo thirſty after the graces of God, but if wee come in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility to him, he will giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſweete graces of his ſpirit to quench them: wherefore let vs put out all carnall doubts, and worldly cares, and ſet our ſelues to performe our duties, and wee
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14910:43"/> vndoubtedly be perſwaded to finde his mercies. For hee that bids vs forgiue our bretheren ſeauenty times ſeauen times if they ſeeke vnto vs; much more will God forgiue vs all our ſinnes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, bee they neuer ſo many, nor neuer ſo great, if wee ſeeke vnto him, by true repentance, and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them with griefe and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
            <p>If hee would ſeeke <hi>Paul</hi> when hee was going to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> to perſecute the members of Chriſt, and ſhew him mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; how much more will hee ſhew com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to ſuch, which now haue deſiſted from perſecuting of the Sains, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of other ſinnes, and labour to ſeeke God by true repentance, and a full reſolution to ſerue him in truth.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, if God would call for <hi>Adam,</hi> when hee ranne from from him to hide himſelfe, and all to giue him the pardon of his ſinne which hee vnhappily had committed; how much more will hee giue all things vnto them both temporall, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, which with an honeſt heart ſeeke
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14910:44"/> vnto him, by true repentance, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorrow for their ſinnes, for if hee bee ſo ready to ſhew mercie to ſuch which neuer ſeeeke for it, hee will bee more ready to giue mercy to ſuch, as in truth performe this doctrine. The time being paſt, let vs here make an end for this time.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14910:44"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
